Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of Teachers PE.012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of Teachers
1925-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.012
5.5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of Teachers (1925-2017) is an artificial collection of materials assembled by the Tamiment Library staff including fliers, pamphlets, constitutions, newspaper clippings and other materials accumulated gradually over the years through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, organizations, and bookstores, and through exchanges with other special library collections and by ongoing collecting by staff.
Custodial History
The provenance of this material is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Records (WAG 022)
United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection (OH 9)
United Federation of Teachers: Italian-American Studies Committee Records (WAG 056)
Charles J. Hendley Papers (Tam 109)
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
I. National Federation Files, 1925-2006
II. Local Files, 1925-2017
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The American Federation of Teachers (AFT) was founded in 1916, in Chicago, Illinois, and has been affiliated with the American Federation of Labor (AFL), and later the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), since it's founding. Membership was effected by anti-communist efforts following both World War I and World War II, and members cooperated in many strikes from the 1940s through the 1970s. The AFT has advocated for teacher training, educational reforms, and for human and civil rights.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of Teachers (1925-2017) consist of constitutions, contracts, agreements, by-laws, memoranda, reports, and printed ephemera such as clippings, flyers, broadsides, leaflets, catalogs, press releases, programs, and pamphlets generated by federations and national, regional and local bodies, as well as departments and divisions of the National Federation of Teachers. While a small portion of the material is international in scope or associated with other regions of the United States, the majority of the collection relates to the New York metropolitan area.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Printed ephemera.; Memorandums.; Pamphlets.; Collective labor agreements.; Clippings (information artifacts); Constitutions.; Workers Education Local 189 (U.S.); Local 3882 United Staff Association of New York University; American Federation of Teachers; Selden, David
- Series I: National Federation Files, 1925-2006; 4 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons
  - Annual Report, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1984-1896 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1933-1954 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1966-1974 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1977-1988 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Convention I, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Convention I, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Convention I, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Convention I, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Convention I, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Convention I, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Convention II, 1967` (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Convention, 2006 (Box 2)
  - 1925 (Box 2)
  - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1952-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970-1978 (Box 2)
  - 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - Adult Education Committee, undated (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee on Higher Education, undated (Box 2)
  - Agreement: AFT Staff Union/AFT, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - American Educator, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Benefits, undated (Box 3)
  - California Federation of Teachers, 2002 (Box 3)
  - California Federation of Teachers: Community College Council, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Collective Bargaining, undated (Box 3)
  - Community College Guild Reporter, 1956-1959, undated (Box 3)
  - Directories, 1966-1975 (Box 3)
  - Elections, 1962, undated (Box 3)
  - Empire State Federation of Teachers, 1943-1950 (Box 3)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Florida Education Association/United I, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Florida Education Association/United II, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Freedom School Project, 1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Hawaii Federation of College Teachers, undated (Box 3)
  - Illinois Federation of Teachers, 1962-1993 (Box 3)
  - Lake Shore Federation of Teachers (St. Clair Shores, MI), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Manual for Locals, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Massachusetts State Branch, 1937-1943 (Box 3)
  - Merit Ratings, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Mount Vernon Federation of Teachers, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications I, 1942-1969 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications II, 1942-1969 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1970-1978, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Public Relations Department, 1978-1985 (Box 3)
  - Publications on, 1978 (Box 3)
  - QUEST - Council for Quality Educational Standards, 1968-1976 (Box 3)
  - Rank and File, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
  - Referendums, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Salary Surveys, 1955-1959 (Box 3)
  - Salary Surveys, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Seldon, David, 1969-1998 (Box 4)
  - United Action Caucus, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - United Teachers of New York State, 1971 (Box 4)
- Series II: Local Records, 1925-2017; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Local 1 (Chicago, IL), 1937-1968 (Box 4)
  - Local 3 (Philadelphia, PA), 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - Local 4 (Gary IN): Gary Referendum, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Local 5 (New York, NY), 1938-1941, undated (Box 4)
  - Local 6 (Washington, DC), 1969 (Box 4)
  - Local 61 (San Francisco), 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1941-1945 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1946-1950 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1953-1956 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 12)
  - Local 189 Workers Education: Directory of Labor Education, 1971-1998 (Box 4)
  - Local 189 Workers Education: Directory of Workers Education, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Local 194 (Mena, AK), 1940 (Box 4)
  - Local 212 (Washington, DC), 1969 (Box 4)
  - Local 231 (Detroit, MI), 1958-1969 (Box 4)
  - Local 238 (Minneapolis, MN), 1948 (Box 4)
  - Local 394 (Hammond, IN), 1950 (Box 4)
  - Local 400 (Pittsburgh, PA), 1972-1978 (Box 4)
  - Local 420 (St. Louis, MO), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Local 430 (Los Angeles, CA), 1948 (Box 4)
  - Local 441 (Boston, MA), 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - Local 453 (WPA Teachers Union, New York), 1937, undated (Box 4)
  - Local 481 (Newark, NJ), 1975 (Box 4)
  - Local 484 (Springfield, MA), 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Local 500 (Penn State), 1953 (Box 4)
  - Local 537 (New York College Teachers Union), 1939-1940, undated (Box 4)
  - Local 555 (New York), 1953, undated (Box 4)
  - Local 571 (Cicero, IL), 1968 (Box 4)
  - Local 616 (Rochester), undated (Box 4)
  - Local 484 (Highland Park, MI), 1971 (Box 4)
  - Local 781 (Kingston, NY), 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - Local 803 (Schenectady, NY), 1966-1971 (Box 4)
  - Local 842 (Utica, NY), 1951 (Box 4)
  - Local 886 (Kankakee, IL), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Local 933 (New Haven), 1969 (Box 4)
  - Local 1085 (Taylor Township, MN), 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Local 1258 (Salem, MA), 1968 (Box 4)
  - Local 1261 (Lay Faculty Association, Flushing, NY), 1984 (Box 4)
  - Local 1274 (Niles Township, IL), 1973-1976 (Box 4)
  - Local 1391 (Chicago Heights, IL), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Local 1460 (United Federation of College Teachers, New York, NY), 1967-1973, undated (Box 4)
  - Local 1460 (United Federation of College Teachers, New York, NY) I, circa 1972 (Box 4)
  - Local 1460 (United Federation of College Teachers, New York, NY) II, circa 1972 (Box 4)
  - Local 1460 (United Federation of College Teachers, New York, NY), 1973, undated (Box 5)
  - Local 1521 (College Staff Guild, Los Angeles, CA), 1987 (Box 5)
  - Local 1600 (Cook County College, Chicago, IL), 1967-1970 (Box 5)
  - Local 1633 (Valley Stream Federation of Teachers, NY), undated (Box 5)
  - Local 1708 (Federation of College Clerical and Technical Personnel, Chicago, IL), 1988 (Box 5)
  - Local 1769 (Bryant College Faculty Federation, R.I.), 1969 (Box 5)
  - Local 1845 (Onondaga Community College), 1968-1971 (Box 5)
  - Local 1871 (Rockland Community College Federation of Teachers), 1969 (Box 5)
  - Local 1980 (Community College of Baltimore, MD), 1971 (Box 5)
  - Local 2026 (Community College of Philadelphia, PA), 1985 (Box 5)
  - Local 3271 (Wisconsin Federation of Teachers), 1977-1979 (Box 5)
  - Local 3457 (Fashion Institute of Technology, New York, NY), 1967-1985 (Box 5)
  - Local 3550 (Graduate Employees Organization), 1996-1999 (Box 5)
  - Local 3605 (Western Wisconsin Technical College), undated (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1982-1987 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1985-1987 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University) I, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University) II, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1989 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1990 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1993 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1994 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University), 2010-2017, undated (Box 5, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 13)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Circular Letters, undated (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1981-1996 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Employee Orientation Packet, 1978-1991 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): "NYU-Opoly", undated (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 5)
  - Local 3882 (United Staff Association of New York University): Strike, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Local 3998 (Long Island University), 1975-1979 (Box 5)
  - Local 4200 (CT), 1984-1987 (Box 5)